Chapter 54.
The town hose story.
as told at the Golden Inn.
The Cape of Good Hope and all the watery region about out there is much like some
noted four corners of a great highway, where you meet more travelers than in
any other part. It was not very long after speaking the goon that another
homewardbound whaleman, the town hoe, was encountered. She was manned almost
wholly by Polynesians.
In the short gam that ensued, she gave us strong news of Moby Dick. To some,
the general interest in the white whale was now wildly heightened by a
circumstance of the town ho story, which seemed obscurely to involve with the
whale a certain wondrous inverted visitation of one of those so-called
judgments of God, which are at times said to overtake some men. This latter
circumstance, with its own particular accompaniment, forming what may be
called the secret part of the tragedy about to be narrated, never reached the
ears of Captain Ahab or his mates, for that secret part of the story was
unknown to the captain of the town Hoe himself. It was the private property of
three Confederate white seaman of that ship, one of whom, it seems,
communicated it to Tashego with roish injunctions of secrecy. But the
following night Tashego rambled in his sleep, and revealed so much of it in
that way that when he was wakened, he could not well withhold the rest.
Nevertheless, so potent an influence did this thing have on those seammen in the
Peekquad who came to the full knowledge of it, and by such a strange delicacy,
to call it so, were they governed in this matter, that they kept the secret
among themselves, so that it never transpired a bath the Peekquad's main
mast. interweaving in its proper place this darker thread with the story as
publicly narrated on the ship, the whole of this strange affair, I now proceed to
put on lasting record.
Footnote: Town Hoe, the ancient whale cry upon first sighting a whale from the
mast head, still used by whalemen in hunting the famous Galopagus terrapin.
End of footnote.
For my humor's sake, I shall preserve the style in which I once narrated it at
Lima, to a lounging circle of my Spanish friends, one Saints Eve, smoking upon
the thick guilt tiled piaza of the golden inn. Of those fine cavaliers, the
young Dons's Pedro and Sebastian were on closer terms with me, and hence the
interluding questions they occasionally put, and which are duly answered at the time.
Quote, "Some 2 years prior to my first learning the events which I am about
rehearsing to you, gentlemen, the town hoe, sperm whaler of Nantucket, was
cruising in your Pacific here, not very many days sail eastward from the eaves
of this good golden inn. She was somewhere to the northward of the line.
One morning, upon handling the pumps, according to daily usage, it was
observed that she made more water in her hold than common. They supposeded a
swordfish had stabbed her gentleman, but the captain, having some unusual reason
for believing that rare good luck awaited him in those latitudes, and
therefore being very averse to quit them, and the leak not being then
considered at all dangerous, though indeed they could not find it after
searching the hold as low down as was possible in rather heavy weather, the
ship still continued her cruisings, the mariners working at the pumps at wide
died in easy intervals.
But no good luck came. More days went by, and not only was the leak yet
undiscovered, but it sensibly increased, so much so that, now taking some alarm,
the captain, making all sail, stood away for the nearest harbor among the
islands, there to have his hull ho out and repaired.
Though no small passage was before her, yet if the communist chance favored, he
did not at all fear that his ship would found her by the way, because his pumps
were of the best, and being periodically relieved at them, those six and 30 men
of his could easily keep the ship free, never mind if the leak should double on
her. In truth, well nigh the whole of this passage, being attended by very
prosperous breezes, the town hall had all but certainly arrived in perfect
safety at her port, without the occurrence of the least fatality, had it
not been for the brutal overbearing of Radney, the mate, a vineyard, and the
bitterly provoked vengeance of Steelkilt, a lakeman and desperado from Buffalo.
Lakeman, buffalo, pray. What is a lakeman? And where is buffalo? said Don
Sebastian, rising in his swinging mat of grass.
On the eastern shore of our Lake Eerie, Dawn, but I crave your courtesy. Uh,
maybe you shall soon hear further of all that.
Now, gentlemen, in square sail brigs and threemasted ships, well, nigh as large
and stout as any that ever sailed out of your old cayo to far Manila, this
lakeman, in the landlocked heart of our America, had yet been nurtured by all
those agrarian free booting impressions popularly connected with the open ocean.
For in their interflowing aggregate those grand freshwater seas of ours,
Eerie and Ontario and Hurine and Superior and Michigan, possess an
oceanlike expansiveness with many of the ocean's noblest traits, with many of its
rimmed varieties of races and of clims.
They contain round archipelos of romantic isles, even as the Polynesian
waters do, in large part are shored by two great contrasting nations, as the
Atlantic is. They furnish long maritime approaches to our numerous territorial
colonies from the east, dotted all round their banks, here and there, are frowned
upon by batteries, and by the goatlike craggy guns of Lofty Macheno. They have
heard the fleet thunderings of naval victories. At intervals they yield their
beaches to wild barbarians whose red painted faces flash from out their
poultry wigwams. For leagues and leagues are flanked by ancient and unentered
forests where the gaunt pines stand like seried lines of kings and gothic genealogies.
Those same woods harboring wild Africs of prey and silken creatures whose
exported furs give robes to tartar emperors. They mirror the paved capitals
of Buffalo and Cleveland as well as Wnebago villages. They float alike the
fullrigged merchant ship, the armed cruiser of the state, the steamer and
the beach canoe. They are swept by boran and dismasting blasts as direful as any
that lash the salted wave. They know what shipwrecks are, for out of sight of
land, however inland they have drowned full many a midnight ship with all its
shrieking crew. Thus, gentlemen, though an inlander, Steelkilt was wild ocean
and wild ocean nurtured, as much of an audacious mariner as any. And for
Radney, though in his infancy he may have laid him down on the lone Nantucket
beach to nurse at his maternal sea, though in afterlife he had long followed
our austere Atlantic and your contemplative Pacific, yet he was quite
as vengeful and full of social quarrel as the backwoods seaman, fresh from the
latitudes of buckhornh handled buoy knives. Yet was this Nantucketer a man
with some good-hearted traits, and this lakeman a mariner, who though a sort of
devil indeed, might yet by inflexible firmness, only tempered by that common
decency of human recognition, which is the meanest slaves, right? Thus treated,
this steel kilt had long been retained harmless and dosile. At all events he
had proved so thus far, but Radney was doomed and made mad and steel killed.
But gentlemen, you shall hear.
It was not more than a day or two at the furthest after pointing her prow for her
island haven that the town hose leak seemed again increasing, but only so as
to require an hour or more at the pumps every day. You must know that in a
settled and civilized ocean like our Atlantic, for example, some skippers
think little of pumping their whole way across it, though of a still sleepy
night, should the officer of the deck happen to forget his duty in that
respect, the probability would be that he and his shipmates would never again
remember it, on account of all hands gently subsiding to the bottom. Nor in
the solitary and savage seas far from you to the westward, gentlemen, is it
altogether unusual for ships to keep clanging at their pump handles in full
chorus, even for a voyage of considerable length, that is, if it lie
along a tolerably accessible coast, or if any other reasonable retreat is
afforded them. It is only when a leaky vessel is in some very out of the way
part of those waters, some really landless latitude, that her captain
begins to feel a little anxious.
Much this way had it been with the town hoe. So when her leak was found gaining
once more, there was in truth some small concern manifested by several of her
company, especially by Radney the mate.
He commanded the upper sails to be well hoisted, sheetated home a new, and every
way expanded to the breeze.
Now this Radney, I suppose, was as little of a coward, and as little
inclined to any sort of nervous apprehensiveness touching his own
person, as any fearless, unthinking creature on land or on sea that you can
conveniently imagine, gentlemen.
Therefore, when he betrayed this solicitude about the safety of the ship,
some of the seaman declared that it was only on account of his being a part
owner in her. So when they were working that evening at the pumps, there was on
this head no small gamesomeness slightly going on among them, as they stood with
their feet continually overflowed by the rippling clear water, clear as any
mountain spring, gentlemen, that bubbling from the pumps ran across the
deck, and poured itself out in steady spouts at the Lee scupper holes.
Now, as you well know, it is not seldom the case in this conventional world of
ours, watery or otherwise, that when a person placed in command over his fellow
men, finds one of them to be very significantly his superior in general
pride of manhood, straightway against that man, he conceives an unconquerable
dislike and bitterness. and if he have a chance, he will pull down and pulverize
that subalter's tower and make a little heap of dust of it. Be this conceit of
mine as it may, gentlemen, at all events, Steelkilt was a tall and noble
animal with a head like a Roman, and a flowing golden beard like the tassled
housings of your last viceroyy's snorting charger, and a brain, and a
heart, and a soul in him, gentlemen, which had made steel kilt Charlemagne,
had he been born son to Charlemagne's father. But Radney, the mate, was as
ugly as a mule, yet as hearty, as stubborn, as malicious. He did not love
Steelkilt, and Steelkilt knew it.
Aspying the mate drawing near as he was toiling at the pump with the rest, the
lakemen affected not to notice him, but unawed went on with his gay banterings.
"I I my merry lads, it's a lively leak this. Hold a canakin, one of you, and
let's have a taste. By the Lord, it's worth bottling. I tell you what, men,
old Rad's investment must go for it. He had best cut away his part of the hull
and tow it home. The fact is, boys, that swordfish only began the job. He's come
back again with a gang of ship carpenters, sawfish, and file fish and
whatnot. And the whole posi of them are now hard at work cutting and slashing
the bottom, making improvements. I suppose if old Rad were here now, I'd
tell him to jump overboard and scatter them. They're playing the devil with his
estate, I can tell him. But he's a simple old soul, Rad. And a beauty, too,
boys. They say the rest of his property is invested in looking glasses. I wonder
if he'd give a poor devil like me the model of his nose.
Damn your eyes. What's that pump stopping for? Roared Radney, pretending
not to have heard the sailor's talk.
Thunder away at it. I I sir, said Steelkilt, merry as a cricket. Lively,
boys. Lively now. And with that the pump clanged like 50 fire engines. The men
tossed their hats off to it and airong that peculiar gasping of the lungs was
heard which denotes the fullest tensions of life's utmost energies.
Quitting the pump at last with the rest of his band, the lakeman went forward,
all panting, and sat himself down on the windless, his face fiery red, his eyes
bloodshot, and wiping the profuse sweat from his brow.
Now what cousining fiend it was, gentleman, that possessed Radney to
meddle with such a man in that corporeally exasperated state, I know
not. But so it happened. Intolerably striding along the deck, the mate
commanded him to get a broom and sweep down the planks and also a shovel and
remove some offensive matters consequent upon allowing a pig to run at large.
Now gentlemen, sweeping a ship's deck at sea is a piece of household work which
in all times but raging gales is regularly attended to every evening. It
has been known to be done in the case of ships actually foundering at the time.
Such gentlemen is the inflexibility of sea usages and the instinctive love of
neatness in seammen, some of whom would not willingly drown without first
washing their faces. But in all vessels this broom business is the prescriptive
province of the boys, if boys there be aboard. Besides, it was the stronger men
in the town hoe that had been divided into gangs, taking turns at the pumps,
and being the most athletic seaman of them all, Steelkilt had been regularly
assigned captain of one of the gangs.
Consequently, he should have been freed from any trivial business not connected
with truly nodical duties, such being the case with his comrades. I mention
all of these particulars so that you may understand exactly how this affair stood
between the two men.
But there was more than this. The order about the shovel was almost as plainly
meant to sting and insult Steelkilt as though Radney had spat in his face. Any
man who has gone sailor in a whale ship will understand this. And all this, and
doubtless much more, the lakeman fully comprehended when the mate uttered his
command. But as he sat still for a moment, and as he steadfastly looked
into the mate's malignant eye, and perceived the stacks of powder casks
heaped up in him, and the slow match silently burning along towards them, as
he instinctively saw all this, that strange forbearance and unwillingness to
stir up the deeper passionateness in any alreadyful being, a repugnance most
felt, when felt at all, by really valiant men, even when agrieved, this
nameless phantom feeling gentleman stole over steel kilts. Therefore, in his
ordinary tone, only a little broken by the bodily exhaustion he was temporarily
in, he answered him, saying that sweeping the deck was not his business,
and he would not do it. And then, without at alluding to the shovel, he
pointed to three lads as the customary sweepers, who, not being billeted at the
pumps, had done little or nothing all day. To this, Radney replied with an
oath, in a most doineering and outrageous manner, unconditionally
reiterating his command, meanwhile advancing upon the still seated lakemen,
with an uplifted Cooper's club hammer, which he had snatched from a cask nearby.
Heated and irritated as he was by his spasmodic toil at the pumps, for all his
first nameless feeling of forbearance, the sweating steel kilt could but ill
brookke this bearing in the mate. But somehow still smothering the
confflgration within him, without speaking, he remained doggedly rooted to
his seat, till at last the incensed Radney shook the hammer within a few
inches of his face, furiously commanding him to do his bidding.
Steelkilt rose, and slowly retreating round the windless, steadily followed by
the mate with his menacing hammer, deliberately repeated his intention not
to obey. Seeing, however, that his forbearance had not the slightest
effect, by an awful and unspeakable intimation with his twisted hand, he
warned off the foolish and infatuated man. But it was to no purpose, and in
this way the two went once slowly round the windless, when resolved at last no
longer to retreat, bethinking him that he had now forebornne as much as
comported with his humor, the lakeman paused on the hatches, and thus spoke to the officer.
"Mr. Radney, I will not obey you. Take that hammer away, or look to yourself."
But the predestinated mate, coming still closer to him, where the lakeman stood
fixed, now shook the heavy hammer within an inch of his teeth, meanwhile
repeating a string of insufferable maledictions, retreating not the thousandth part of an
inch, stabbing him in the eye with the unflinching punard of his glance,
Steelkilt, clenching his right hand behind him, and creepingly drawing it
back, told his persecutor that if the hammer but grazed his cheek. He
steelkilt would murder him. But gentlemen, the fool had been branded for
the slaughter by the gods. Immediately the hammer touched his cheek. The next
instant the lower jaw of the mate was stove in his head. He fell on the hatch,
spouting blood like a whale.
Air the cry could go a steel kilt was shaking one of the backstays leading far
along to where two of his comrades were standing their mast heads. They were both canalers.
Canalers? cried Don Pedro. We have seen many whale ships in our harbors, but
never heard of your canalers. Pardon?
Who and what are they? Canalers? Don, are the boatman belonging to our grand
eerie canal? You must have heard of it.
Nay, Senor, hereabouts in this dull, warm, most lazy, and hereditary land, we
know but little of your vigorous north.
I Well, then, Don, refill my cup. Your chicha very fine, and air proceeding
further, I will tell you what our canalers are, for such information may
throw sidlight upon my story.
For 360 mi, gentlemen, through the entire breadth of the state of New York,
through numerous populous cities and most thriving villages, through long,
dismal, uninhabited swamps and affluent cultivated fields unrivaled for
fertility, by billiard room and bar room, through the holy of holies of
great forests, on Roman arches over Indian rivers, through sun and shade, by
happy hearts are broken, Through all the wide contrasting scenery of those noble
Mohawk counties, and especially by rows of snow white chapels, whose spires
stand almost like milestones, flows one continual stream of Venetianly corrupt
and often lawless life. There is your true ashante, gentlemen. There howl your
pagans, where you ever find them, next door to you, under the long-flung shadow
and the snug, patronizing lee of churches. For by some curious fatality,
as it is often noted of your metropolitan free booters that they ever
encamp around the halls of justice, so sinners, gentlemen, most abound in holiest vicinities.
Is that a frier passing? said Don Pedro, looking downwards into the crowded piaza
with humorous concern.
Well, for our northern friend, dim Isabella's inquisition waines in Lima,
laughed Don Sebastian. Proceed, Senor, a moment, pardon, cried another of the
company. In the name of all us limies, I but desired to express to you, sir
sailor, that we have by no means overlooked your delicacy in not
substituting present Lima for distant Venice in your corrupt comparison. Oh
no, do not bow and look surprised. You know the proverb along all this coast,
corrupt as Lima, it but bears out your saying, too. Churches more plentiful
than billiard tables and forever open and corrupt as Lima. So too, Venice, I
have been there. The holy city of the blessed evangelist, St. Mark. St.
Dominic, purge it. Your cup. Thanks.
Here I refill. Now you pour out again.
Freely depicted in his own vocation, gentlemen. The canaler would make a fine
dramatic hero. So abundantly and picturesely wicked is he like Mark
Anthony for days and days along his green turfed flowery Nile he indolently
floats openly toying with his red cheicked Cleopatra ripening his apricot
thigh upon the sunny deck. But a sure all this effeminy is dashed. The
brigandish guise which the canaler so proudly sports. His slouched and gay
ribboned hat betoken his grand features.
A terror to the smiling innocence of the villages through which he floats. His
swart viz and bold swagger are not unshunned in cities. Once a vagabond on
his own canal, I have received good turns from one of these canalers. I
thanked him heartily. Would feain not be ungrateful, but it is often one of the
prime redeeming qualities of your man of violence, that at times he is as stiff
an armed to back a poor stranger in a straight as to plunder a wealthy one. In
some gentlemen, what the wildness of this canal life is is emphatically
evinced by this, that our wild whale fishery contains so many of its most
finished graduates, and that scarce any race of mankind except Sydney men are so
much distrusted by our whailing captains. Nor does it at all diminish
the curiousness of this matter that to many thousands of our rural boys and
young men born along its line, the probationary life of the Grand Canal
furnishes the sole transition between quietly reaping in a Christian cornfield
and recklessly plowing the waters of the most barbaric seas.
I see, I see, impetuously exclaimed Don Pedro, spilling his chicha upon his
silvery ruffles. No need to travel. The world's one lemur. I had thought now
that at your temperate north, the generations were cold and holy as the hills. But the story
I left off, gentlemen, where the lakemen shook the backstay, hardly had he done
so, when he was surrounded by the three junior mates and the four harpooners,
who all crowded him to the deck, but sliding down the ropes like baleful
comets, the two canalers rushed into the uproar, and sought to drag their man out
of it toward the folks. Others of the sailors joined with them in this
attempt, and a twisted turmoil ensued.
While standing out of harm's way, the valiant captain danced up and down with
a whale pike, calling upon his officers to manhandle that atrocious scoundrel,
and smoke him along to the quarter deck.
At intervals he ran close up to the revolving border of the confusion, and
prying into the heart of it with his pike, sought to prick out the object of
his resentment. But Steelkilt and his desperadoos were too much for them all.
They succeeded in gaining the folks deck where, hastily sooing about three or
four large casks in a line with the windless, these sea Parisians entrenched
themselves behind the barricade.
Come out of that, you pirates, roared the captain, now menacing them with a
pistol in each hand just brought to him by the steward. Come out of that, you cutthroats.
Steelkilt leaped on the barricade, and striding up and down there, defied the
worst the pistols could do, but gave the captain to understand distinctly that
his Steel Kilt's death would be the signal for a murderous mutiny on the
part of all hands. Fearing in his heart, lest this might prove but too true, the
captain a little desisted, but still commanded the insurgents instantly to
return to their duty. Will you promise not to touch us if we do? demanded their
ringleer. Turn two. Turn two. I make no promise. To your duty. Do you want to
sink the ship by knocking off at a time like this? Turn two. And he once more
raised a pistol. Sink the ship, cried Steelkilt. I let her sink. Not a man of
us turns two, unless you swear not to raise a rope yarn against us. What say
you men? Turning to his comrades, a fierce cheer was their response.
The lakemen now patrolled the barricade, all the while keeping his eye on the
captain and jerking out such sentences as these. It's not our fault. We didn't
want it. I told him to take his hammer away. It was Boy's business. He might
have known me before this. I told him not to prick the buffalo. I believe I
have broken a finger here against his cursed jaw. Ain't those mincing knives
down the fsil there, men? Look to those hand spikes, my hearties. Captain, by
God, look to yourself. Say the word and don't be a fool. Forget it all. We are
ready to turn to treat us decently and we're your men, but we won't be flogged.
Turn. I make no promises. Turn two, I say.
Look you now," cried the lakemen, flinging out his arms towards him.
"There are a few of us here, and I am one of them, who have shipped for the
cruise, do you see? Now, as you well know, sir, we can claim our discharge as
soon as the anchor is down. So, we don't want a row. It's not our interest. We
want to be peaceable. We're ready to work, but we won't be flogged." "Turn
two," roared the captain. Steelkilt glanced round him a moment and then
said, "I tell you what it is now, Captain. Rather than kill you and be
hung for such a shabby rascal, we won't lift a hand against you unless you
attack us. But till you say the word about not flogging us, we don't do a hand's turn."
Down into the folks, then down with you.
I'll keep you there till you're sick of it. Down you go. Shall we? cried the
ring leader to his men. Most of them were against it, but at length, in
obedience to Steelkill, they preceded him down into their dark den, growlingly
disappearing like bears into a cave.
As the lakeman's bare head was just level with the planks, the captain and
his posi leaped the barricade, and rapidly drawing over the slide of the
scuttle, planted their group of hands upon it, and loudly called for the
steward to bring the heavy brass padlock belonging to the companion way. Then
opening the slide a little, the captain whispered something down the crack,
closed it, and turned the key upon them, 10 in number, leaving on deck some 20 or
more, who thus far had remained neutral.
All night a wide awake watch was kept by all the officers forward and aft,
especially about the folks scuttle and for hatchway, at which last place was
feared the insurgents might emerge after breaking through the bulkhead below. But
the hours of darkness passed in peace.
The men who still remained at their duty toiling hard at the pumps, whose
clinking and clanking at intervals through the dreary night, dismally
resounded through the ship. At sunrise the captain went forward, and knocking
on the deck, summoned the prisoners to work, but with a yell they refused.
Water was then lowered down to them, and a couple of handfuls of biscuit were
tossed after it. When again turning the key upon them and pocketing it, the
captain returned to the quarter deck.
Twice every day for three days this was repeated. But on the fourth morning a
confused wrangling, and then a scuffling was heard as the customary summons was
delivered, and suddenly four men burst up from the folil saying they were ready
to turn two. The feted closeness of the air and a famishing diet united perhaps
to some fears of ultimate retribution had constrained them to surrender at
discretion. Emboldened by this, the captain reiterated his demand to the
rest, but Steelkilt shouted to him a terrific hint to stop his babbling and
betake himself where he belonged. On the fifth morning, three others of the
mutineers bolted up into the air from the desperate arms below that sought to
restrain them. Only three were left.
"Better turn two now," said the captain with a heartless jeer. "Shut us up
again, will you?" cried Steelkilt. "Oh, certainly," the captain, and the key clicked.
It was at this point, gentlemen, that, enraged by the defection of seven of his
former associates, and stung by the mocking voice that had last hailed him,
and maddened by his long intunement in a place as black as the bowels of despair.
It was then that Steelkilled proposed to the two canalers, thus far apparently of
one mind with him, to burst out of their hole at the next summoning of the
garrison, and armed with their keen mincing knives, long crescentic, heavy
implements with a handle at each end, run a muck from Bowsprit to Taffrell,
and if by any devilishness of desperation possible, seize the ship.
For himself he would do this, he said, whether they joined him or not. That was
the last night he should spend in that den. But the scheme met with no
opposition on the part of the other two.
They swore they were ready for that, or for any other mad thing, for anything in
short but a surrender. And what was more, they each insisted on being the
first man on deck when the time to make the rush should come. But to this their
leader has fiercely objected, reserving that priority for himself, particularly
as his two comrades would not yield the one to the other in the matter, and both
of them could not be first, for the latter would but admit one man at a
time. And here, gentlemen, the foul play of these miscreants must come out. Upon
hearing the frantic project of their leader, each in his own separate soul
had suddenly lighted, it would seem, upon the same piece of treachery, namely
to be foremost in breaking out in order to be the first of the three, though the
last of the 10, to surrender, and thereby secure whatever small chance of
pardon such conduct might merit. But when Steelkilt made known his
determination still to lead them to the last, they in some way, by some subtle
chemistry of villain, mixed their before secret treacheries together, and when
their leader fell into a doze, verbally opened their souls to each other in
three sentences, and bound the sleeper with cords, and gagged him with cords,
and shrieked out for the captain at midnight.
Thinking murder at hand, and smelling in the dark for the blood, he and all his
armed mates and harpooners rushed for the folks. In a few minutes the scuttle
was opened, and bound hand and foot, the still struggling ringleer was shoved up
into the air by his perfidious allies, who at once claimed the honor of
securing a man who had been fully ripe for murder. But all these were collared
and dragged along the deck like dead cattle, and side by side were seized up
into the mizenrigging like three quarters of meat. And there they hung
till morning. "Damn ye!" cried the captain, pacing to and fro before them.
"The vultures would not touch you, you villains!"
At sunrise he summoned all hands, and separating those who had rebelled from
those who had taken no part in the mutiny, he told the former that he had a
good mind to fogg them all round, thought upon the whole he would do so.
He ought to. Justice demanded it. But for the present, considering their
timely surrender, he would let them go with a reprimand, which he accordingly
administered in the vernacular.
But as for you, you carrying rogues, turning to the three men in the rigging,
for you? I mean to mince you up for the tripots.
And seizing a rope, he applied it with all his might to the backs of the two
traitors, till they yelled no more, but lifelessly hung their heads sideways as
the two crucified thieves are drawn. "My wrist is sprained with you," he cried at
last. But there is still rope enough left for you, my fine banttom, that
wouldn't give up. Take that gag from his mouth, and let us hear what he can say
for himself.
For a moment the exhausted mutineer made a tremulous motion of his cramped jaws,
then painfully twisting round his head, said in a sort of hiss, "What I say is
this, and mind it well. If you fogg me, I murder you.
Say you so? See then how you frighten me. And the captain drew off with the
rope to strike.
Best not, hissed the lakemen.
But I must, and the rope was once more drawn back for the stroke. Steelkilled
here hissed out something inaudible to all but the captain who to the amazement
of all hands started back paced the deck rapidly two or three times and then
suddenly throwing down his rope said I won't do it let him go cut him down do
you hear as the junior mates were hurrying to execute the order a pale man with a
bandaged head arrested them Radney the chief mate. Ever since the blow he
had lain in his birth, but that morning hearing the tumult on the deck, he had
crept out, and thus far had watched the whole scene. Such was the state of his
mouth that he could hardly speak, but mumbling something about his being
willing and able to do what the captain dared not attempt, he snatched the rope
and advanced to his pinioned foe.
"You are a coward," hissed the lakeman.
So I am, but take that. The mate was in the very act of striking when another
hiss stayed his uplifted arm. He paused, and then, pausing no more, made good his
words, spite of Steelkilt's threat, whatever that might have been. The three
men were then cut down. All hands were turned too, and sullenly worked by the
moody seaman, the iron pumps clanged as before.
Just after dark that day, when one watch had retired below, a clamor was heard in
the folks, and the two trembling traitors running up besieged the cabin
door, saying they dst not consort with the crew, and treaties, cuffs, and kicks
could not drive them back, so at their own instance they were put down in the
ship's run for salvation.
Still, no sign of mutiny reappeared among the rest. On the contrary, it
seemed that mainly at Steelkilts instigation they had resolved to
maintain the strictest peacefulness, obey all orders to the last, and when
the ship reached port, desert her in a body, but in order to ensure the
speediest end to the voyage, they all agreed to another thing, namely not to
sing out for whales in case any should be discovered. for in spite of her leak
and spite of all her other perils, the town hoe still maintained her mast
heads, and her captain was just as willing to lower for a fish at that
moment as on the day his craft first struck the cruising ground, and Radney
the mate was quite as ready to change his birth for a boat, and with his
bandaged mouth, seek to gag in death the vital jaw of the whale.
But though the lakemen had induced the seaman to adopt this sort of passiveness
in their conduct, he kept his own counsel, at least till all was over,
concerning his own proper and private revenge, upon the man who had stung him
in the ventricles of his heart. He was in Radney, the chief mate's watch, and
as if the infatuated man sought to run more than halfway to meet his doom,
after the scene at the rigging, he insisted, against the express council of
the captain, upon resuming the head of his watch at night. Upon this, and one
or two other circumstances, Steelkilt systematically built the plan of his revenge.
During the night, Radney had an unseammanlike way of sitting on the ball
works of the quarter deck, and leaning his arm upon the gunnel of the boat,
which was hoisted up there, a little above the ship's side. In this attitude
it was well known he sometimes dozed.
There was a considerable vacancy between the boat and the ship, and down between
this was the sea. Steelkilt calculated his time and found that his next trick
at the helm would come round at 2:00 in the morning of the third day from that
in which he had been betrayed. At his leisure he employed the interval in
braiding something very carefully in his watches below. "What are you making
there?" said his shipmate. "What do you think? What does it look like?" "Like a
lanyard for your bag, but it's an odd one, seems to me." Yes, rather oddish,
said the lakeman, holding it at arms length before him. But I think it will
answer. Shipmate, I haven't enough twine. Have you any? But there was none
in the folks. And I must get some from
old Rad. And he rose to go a You don't
mean to go a begging to him, said a sailor. Why not? Do you think he won't
do me a turn when it's to help himself in the end, shipmate? And going to the
mate, he looked at him quietly and asked him for some twine to mend his hammock.
It was given him. Neither twine nor lanyard were seen again. But the next
night an iron ball, closely netted, partly rolled from the pocket of the
lakeman's monkey jacket, as he was tucking the coat into his hammock for a
pillow. 24 hours after his trick at the silent helm, nigh to the man who was apt
to doze over the grave always ready dug to the seaman's hand. That fatal hour
was then to come, and in the fordaining soul of steel kilt, the mate was already
stark and stretched as a corpse, with his forehead crushed in.
But, gentlemen, a fool saved the would-be murderer from the bloody deed
he had planned. Yet complete revenge he had, and without being the avenger, for
by a mysterious fatality, heaven itself seemed to step in and take out of his
hands into its own the damning thing he would have done. It was just between
daybreak and sunrise of the morning of the second day, when they were washing
down the decks, that a stupid tener man drawing water in the main chains all at
once shouted out, "There she rolls.
There she rolls. Jeez, you. What a whale. It was Moby Dick.
Moby Dick, cried Don Sebastian. St.
Dominic, sir sailor, but do whales have christenings. Whom call you Moby Dick? A
very white and famous and most deadly immortal monster, Dawn. But that would
be too long a story. How? How? cried all the young Spaniards crowding.
Nay dons dons nay nay I cannot rehearse that now let me get more into the air
sers the chicha the chicha cried Don Pedro our vigorous friend looks faint
fill up his empty glass no need gentleman one moment and I proceed
now gentlemen so suddenly perceiving the snowy whale within 50 yards of the ship
forgetful of the compact among the crew too. In the excitement of the moment,
the Tenerife man had instinctively and involuntarily lifted his voice for the
monster, though for some little time passed it had been plainly beheld from
the three sullen mast heads. All was now a frenzy. "The White Whale! The White
Whale!" was the cry from the captain, mates, and harpooners, who, undeterred
by fearful rumors, were all anxious to capture so famous and precious a fish,
while the dogged crew eyed a scance, and with curses the appalling beauty of the
vast milky mass that lit up by a horizontal spangling sun shifted and
glistened like a living opal in the blue morning sea.
Gentlemen, a strange fatality pervades the whole career of these events, as if
verily mapped out before the world itself was charted. The mutineer was the
bowsman of the mate, and when fast to the fish, it was his duty to sit next to
him, while Radney stood up with his lance in the prow, and haul in or slack
in the line at the word of command.
Moreover, when the four boats were lowered, the mates got the start, and
none howled more fiercely with delight than did steel kilt, as he strained at
his ore. After a stiff pull, their harpooner got fast, and spear in hand,
Radney sprang to the bow. He was always a furious man, it seems, in a boat, and
now his bandaged cry was to beat him on the whale's topmost back. nothing loath
his bowsman hauled him up and up and through a blinding foam that blent two
whitenesses together till of a sudden the boat struck as against a sunken
ledge and keeling over spilled out the standing mate that instant as he fell on
the whale's slippery back the boat writed and was dashed aside by the swell
while Radney was tossed over into the sea on the other flank of the whale he
struck out through the spray and for an inst instant was dimly seen through that
veil, wildly seeking to remove himself from the eye of Moby Dick. But the whale
rushed round in a sudden maelstrom, seized the swimmer between his jaws, and
rearing high up with him, plunged headlong again, and went down.
Meantime, at the first tap of the boat's bottom, the lakeman had slackened the
line, so as to drop a stern from the whirlpool. Calmly looking on, he thought
his own thoughts, but a sudden terrific downward jerking of the boat quickly
brought his knife to the line. He cut it, and the whale was free. But at some
distance, Moby Dick rose again, and with some tatters of Radney's red woolen
shirt caught in the teeth that had destroyed him. All four boats gave chase
again, but the whale eluded them and finally wholly disappeared.
In good time the town hoe reached her port, a savage solitary place where no
civilized creature resided.
There, headed by the lakemen, all but five or six of the forearmsmen
deliberately deserted among the palms, and eventually, as it turned out,
seizing a large double war canoe of the savages, and setting sail for some other harbor.
The ship's company being reduced to but a handful, the captain called upon the
islanders to assist him in the laborious business of heaving down the ship to
stop the leak. But to such unresting vigilance over their dangerous allies
was this small band of whites necessitated both by day and by night.
And so extreme was the hard work they underwent that upon the vessel being
ready again for the sea, they were in such a weakened condition that the
captain Ders not put off with them in so heavy a vessel. After taking counsel
with his officers, he anchored the ship as far offshore as possible, loaded and
ran out his two cannon from the boughs, stacked his musketss on the poop, and
warning the islanders not to approach the ship at their peril, took one man
with him, and setting the sail of his best whaleboat, steered straight before
the wind for Tahiti, 500 mi distant, to procure a reinforcement to his crew.
On the fourth day of the sail, a large canoe was described, which seemed to
have touched at a low aisle of corals.
He steered away from it, but the savage craft bore down on him, and soon the
voice of steel kilt hailed him to heave too, or he would run him underwater. The
captain presented a pistol. With one foot on each prow of the yolked war
canoes, the lakeman laughed him to scorn, assuring him that if the pistol
so much as clicked in the lock, he would bury him in bubbles and foam.
"What do you want of me?" cried the captain.
"Where are you bound? And for what are you bound?" demanded Steelkilt. "No
lies. I am bound to Tahiti for more men." "Very good. Let me board you a
moment. I come in peace. With that, he leaped from the canoe, swam to the boat,
and climbing the gunnel, stood face to face with the captain. Cross your arms,
sir. Throw back your head. Now repeat after me. As soon as Steelkilt leaves
me, I swear to beach this boat on Yonder Island, and remain there 6 days. If I do
not, may lightning strike me.
A pretty scholar, laughed the lakeman.
Adios, Seenor. And leaping into the sea, he swam back to his comrades.
Watching the boat till it was fairly beached and drawn up to the roots of the
coconut trees, Steelkilt made sail again, and in due time arrived at
Tahiti, his own place of destination.
There luck befriended him. Two ships were about to sail for France, and were
providentially in want of precisely that number of men which the sailor headed.
They embarked and so forever got the start of their former captain, had he
been at all minded to work them legal retribution.
Some 10 days after the French ships sailed, the whaleboat arrived, and the
captain was forced to enlist some of the more civilized Tahesians, who had been
somewhat used to the sea. Chartering a small native schooner, he returned with
them to his vessel, and finding all right there, again resumed his
cruisings. Where steel kilt now is, gentlemen, none know. But upon the
island of Nantucket, the widow of Radney still turns to the sea, which refuses to
give up its dead. Still in dreams sees the awful white whale that destroyed him.
"Are you through?" said Don Sebastian quietly. "I am, Don. Then I entreat you.
Tell me if, to the best of your own convictions, this, your story, is in
substance really true. It is so passing wonderful. Did you get it from an
unquestionable source? Bear with me if I seem to press.
Also, bear with all of us, Sir Sailor, for we all join in Don Sebastian's suit,
cried the company with exceeding interest.
Is there a copy of the holy evangelists at the Golden Inn, gentlemen? Nay, said
Don Sebastian, but I know a worthy priest nearby who will quickly procure
one for me. I go for it, but are you well advised? This may grow too serious.
Will you be so good as to bring the priest also, Dawn?
Though there are no auto defays in Lima now, said one of the company to another,
I fear our sailor friend runs risk of the arch episcopy, let us withdraw more
out of the moonlight. I see no need of this. Excuse me for running after you,
Don Sebastian, but may I also beg that you will be particular in procuring the
largestsized evangelists you can.
This is the priest, and he brings you the evangelist, said Don Sebastian,
gravely, returning with a tall and solemn figure.
Let me remove my hat. Now, venerable priest, further into the light, and hold
the holy book before me, that I may touch it. So help me, heaven, and on my
honor, the story I have told you, gentlemen, is in substance and its great
items true. I know it to be true. It happened on this ball. I trod the ship.
I knew the crew. I have seen and talked with Steelkilt since the death of Radney.